Michael Longley papers, 1960-2000
Emory University
Michael Longley papers, 1960-2000
Longley, Michael.
Manuscript Collection No. 744
40 linear ft. (81 boxes) and 14 oversized papers (OP)
Personal and literary papers of Irish poet Michael Longley consisting of manuscripts, correspondence, printed material, photographs, and records relating to the Arts Council of Nothern Ireland. Also includes some materials relating to literary critic Edna Longley.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1992 with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on access
Special restrictions apply: Series 1, Correspondence, letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Finding Aid Note
Index to selected correspondents in Series 1 is available for letters up to 1992.
Biographical Note
Michael Longley was born in Belfast, Northern Ireland, on July 27, 1939. He attended Malone Primary School and the Royal Belfast Academical Institution, before going on to Trinity College, Dublin, where he read Classics. After graduating with honors in 1963, he held a variety of teaching positions in Blackrock, Dublin, London, and Belfast.
It was while teaching in Belfast that Longley first attended Philip Hobsbaum's informal gatherings of writers known simply as "the group." There he and other young writers-including Seamus Heaney, Arthur Terry, Jack Packenham, Harry Chambers-read their poems and short stories and helped to foster the work of a new generation of Irish writers.
Longley published his first collection of poems, Ten Poems, in 1966, followed by Three Regional Voices (1967), Room to Rhyme (with Seamus Heaney and David Hammond, 1968), and Secret Marriages (1968). His first major collection of poems, No Continuing City: Poems 1963-1968, was published in 1969 by Macmillan. Since the 1960's Michael Longley has published numerous collections of poems, among them An Exploded View (1973), Man Lying on the Wall (1976), The Echo Gate (1979), Gorse Fires (1991) and The Ghost Orchid (1995). His Selected Poems, 1963 - 1980 was published in 1981, followed by a later selected edition, Poems, 1963 - 1983 in 1985. After his poetic silence of the 1980s, he published Gorse Fires in 1991 to critical acclaim, followed by The Ghost Orchid (1995), Selected Poems (1998), and The Weather in Japan (2000).
Michael Longley has received numerous awards for his poetry including the Eric Gregory Award in 1965 and, more recently, the 1991 Whitbread Poetry Prize for Gorse Fires as well as the 2000 T.S. Eliot Prize for The Weather in Japan. He was awarded the Queen's Gold Medal for poetry in 2001. He is a member of the Royal Society of Literature and of Aosdána.
In addition to writing poetry, Longley has also edited collections of poems by Louis MacNeice and W.R. Rodgers, and from 1970 - 1991 he directed the literature programs of the Arts Council of Northern Ireland. In 1994 Longley published a collection of autobiographical prose pieces under the title Tuppenny Stung.
He is married to the critic Edna Longley and lives in Belfast.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of personal and literary papers of Michael Longley from 1960-2000. The bulk of the collection contains drafts, typescripts, and proofs of Longley's poems, essays, and prose pieces and works of other authors, most notably Seamus Heaney and Derek Mahon. The collection also contains correspondence, radio and film scripts, printed material, financial records, records relating to Longley's work for the Arts Council of Northern Ireland, and papers of his wife, Edna Longley.
Arrangement Note
Organized into nine series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Writings by Michael Longley, (3) Writings by others, (4) Printed material, (5) Photographs, (6) Financial records, (7) Miscellaneous personal files, (8) Belfast Group sheets, (9) Arts Council of Northern Ireland records, (10) Subject files, and (11) Edna Longley papers.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Adcock, Fleur.; Boland, Eavan.; Carson, Ciaran, 1948-; Dunn, Douglas.; Fallon, Peter, 1951-; Friel, Brian.; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Hobsbaum, Philip.; Johnson, Jennifer, 1930-; McGuckian, Medbh, 1950-; Longley, Edna.; Mahon, Derek, 1941-; Montague, John.; Muldoon, Paul.; Ormsby, Frank, 1947-; Raine, Craig.; Simmons, James, 1933-; Thwaite, Anthony.
Corporate Names
Arts Council of Northern Ireland.; Belfast Group.; John Hewitt International Summer School.
Topical Terms
Arts, Irish.; Belfast Group.; English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Irish poetry--20th century.; Irish poetry--History and criticism.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Women college teachers--Ireland.; Women critics--Ireland.
Geographic Names
Northern Ireland.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Poems.; Screenplays.; Radio scripts.
Occupation
Poet.
Related Materials in This Repository
Seamus Heaney papers, Medbh McGuckian papers, Derek Mahon papers and Paul Muldoon papers.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1960-2000, Series 1; Boxes 1 - 15a
  Scope and Content Note
  The correspondence series of the Michael Longley papers includes letters, telegrams, postcards, and greeting cards both to and from Michael Longley. The earliest items date from 1960, the most recent from 2000. The bulk of the correspondence here is personal or relates to his career as a writer; for correspondence stemming from his career at the Northern Ireland Arts Council, see Series 9. Among the correspondents represented in this series are: Fleur Adcock, Eavan Boland, Ciaran Carson, Douglas Dunn, Gavin Ewart, Peter Fallon, Brian Friel, Seamus Heaney, Philip Hobsbaum, Jennifer Johnston, Medbh McGuckian, Derek Mahon, John Montague, Paul Muldoon, Frank Ormsby, Craig Raine, James Simmons, and Anthony Thwaite. Occasionally Michael Longley's own letters (most often in carbon or in draft form) are also present.
  The correspondence within this series is arranged chronologically, when a date is known. When an item is undated, or when a date is illegible, postmarks have been used to place the item. Those items for which only a month or year is known will be found at the end of the month's or year's sequence, while those items without any indication of date whatsoever are filed at the very end of the chronological arrangement. Undated letters from indexed correspondents are filed alphabetically by writer's name in Box 13. Among these letters is an extensive correspondence with Derek Mahon.
  Finding Aid Note
  Index to selected correspondents in Series 1 is available for letters up to 1992.
  Restrictions on access
  Special restrictions apply: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1979 January - June (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1979 July - December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1980 January - June (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1980 July - December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1981 January - June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1981 July - December (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1982 January - June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1982 July - December (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1983 January - June (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1983 July - December (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1984 January - June (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1984 July - December (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1985 January - March (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1985 April - June (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1985 July - September (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1985 October - December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1986 January - February (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1986 March - April (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1986 May - June (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1986 July - August (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1986 September - November (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1986 December (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1987 January - June (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1987 July - December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1988 January - April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1988 May - July (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1988 August - November (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1988 December (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1989 January - June (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1989 July - November (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1989 December (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1990 January - March (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1990 April - June (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1990 July - October (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1990 November - December (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1991 January - March (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1991 April - June (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1991 July - September (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1991 October - November (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1991 December (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1992 January (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1992 February (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1992 March (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1992 April (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1992 May (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1992 June (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1992 July (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1992 August (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1992 September (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1992 October (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1992 November (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1992 December (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - ca. 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1993 January (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1993 February - December (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1993 Christmas (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1995 January - March (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1995 April - May (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1995 June (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1995 July (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1995 August (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1995 September (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1995 October (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1995 November (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 1995 December (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - circa 1995 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 1996 January (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - 1996 February (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 1996 March (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 1996 April (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1996 May (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1996 June (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1996 July (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1996 August (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1996 September (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1996 October (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1996 November (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1996 December (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - circa 1996 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1997 January (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1997 February (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1997 March (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1997 April (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1997 May (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1997 June (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1997 July (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1997 August (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 1997 September (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - 1997 October - November (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - 1997 December (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - circa 1997 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - 1998 January (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - 1998 February (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - 1998 March (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - 1998 April (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1998 May (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1998 June (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1998 July (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1998 August (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1998 September (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1998 October (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 1998 November (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 1998 December (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - circa 1998 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - 1999 January (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1999 February (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1999 March (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 1999 April (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1999 May (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1999 June (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1999 July (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 1999 August (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 1999 September (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 1999 October (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - 1999 November (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - 1999 December (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - circa 1999 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 2000 January (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 2000 February (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 2000 March (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 2000 April (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 2000 May (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 2000 June (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 2000 July (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 2000 August (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - 2000 September (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - 2000 October (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 2000 November - December (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - circa 2000 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Undated correspondence by Michael Longley (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Undated indexed correspondence, Adcock - McGuckian [Fleur Adcock, Eavan Boland, Ciaron Carson, Paul Durcan, Brian Friel, Puller Grimes, Donald Hall, Philip Hobsbaum, Johnstone, McGuckian] (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Undated indexed correspondence, Mahon (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Undated indexed correspondence, Mahon (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Undated indexed correspondence, Mahon (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Undated indexed correspondence, Montague - Trevor [John Montague, Paul Muldoon, Nuala ni Dhomhnaill, Frank Ormsby, Craig Raine, James Simmons, William Trevor] (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous invitations (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Restricted Correspondence
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1969 - 1976 (Box 15a, Folder 1)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1977 - 1983 (Box 15a, Folder 2)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1984 - 1989 (Box 15a, Folder 3)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1990 - 1994 (Box 15a, Folder 4)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1995 - 2000 (Box 15a, Folder 5)
  - Heaney, Seamus, n.d. (Box 15a, Folder 6)
  - Restricted 20 years from April 2004, per SH review (Box 15a, Folder 7)
- Writings by Michael Longley, circa 1966-2001, Series 2; Boxes 16-43; OP1-4
  The largest portion of the Michael Longley papers is made up of Michael Longley's own writings. This portion of the collection is divided into seven subseries: poetry by Michael Longley, where individual poems are organized by major volume in which they first appeared, and proofs of complete volumes are also included; prose writings; radio and film scripts; works edited by Michael Longley; interviews with Michael Longley; fragments and notes; notebooks.
  The first subseries contains material directly linked to his published collections, drafts of uncollected poems, unpublished / proposed groupings of poems, and unidentified manuscripts. Materials relating to his published collections may include drafts of the book's table of contents, individual poems, complete typescripts, or proofs. The manuscripts of individual poems have been arranged alphabetically by the poem's title. If a poem was known by more than one title, the variant title(s) have been provided in brackets. If a poem was made up of, or included, other poems this is also indicated in brackets, thus [includes... .]. Cross-references are used for those poems that may have manuscript material under more than one title. Drafts are both manuscripts (MS) and typescripts (TS) unless otherwise noted.
  The second subseries is made up of an alphabetical arrangement of Michael Longley's prose writings; essays and reviews by Longley are present as well as lecture notes and notes from public readings of his work. Unidentified poems and prose pieces follow their respective subseries.
  Subseries 2.3 consists primarily of the scripts written by Michael Longley, unless otherwise indicated in brackets, such as [reader] or [conversation with... ]. Such scripts not necessarily written by Longley but which involve him centrally are included here. Works edited by Longley can be found in Subseries 2.4. Subseries 2.5 contains interviews with Michael Longley, mostly in typescript form, often annotated either by the interviewer or Michael Longley. If the interview was published, details are added in brackets.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into six subseries: (2.1) Poems, (2.2) Prose, (2.3) Radio and film scripts, (2.4) Works edited by Michael Longley, (2.5) Interviews, and (2.6) Notebooks.
  - Poems,circa 1968-2000, Subseries 2.1; Boxes 16-34; OP1-4
    - Collected poems, 1968-2000, Subseries 2.1a; Boxes 16-27; OP1-4
      - Room to Rhyme (1968)
      - Room to Rhyme, proofs with corrections (Box OP1)
      - Secret Marriages (1968)
      - Secret Marriages, notes (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Secret Marriages, typescript (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Secret Marriages, wrappers (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - No Continuing City (1969)
      - "Camouflage" (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - "The Centaurs" (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - "Christopher at Birth" [variant title: "For Christopher at Birth"] (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - "Circe" (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - "Dr. Johnson Dying" (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - "Dr. Johnson on the Hebrides" (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - "Emily Dickinson" (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - "En Route" (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - "Epithalamion" (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - "For Edna" [variant title: "For My Daughter"] (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - "The Freemartin" (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - "Freeze-Up" [See also Uncollected poems, "Three Poems about Birds"] (Box 16, Folder 15)
      - "Gathering Mushrooms" [variant title: "Another Harvest"] (Box 16, Folder 16)
      - "Graffiti" (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - "A Headstone" (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - "The Hebrides" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "In a Convent Cemetery" [variant title: "A Convent Cemetery"] (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - "In Memoriam" [variant titles: "In Memoriam R.C.L.," "In Memory of Richard Longley"] (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - "Journey Out of Essex" [variant titles: "Journey From Essex," "Skylight," "To John Clare"] (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - "Klondike" (Box 16, Folder 23)
      - "Leaving Inishmore" [variant title: "Leaving Aran"] (Box 16, Folder 24)
      - "Man Friday" (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - "Narcissus" (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - "Nausicaa" [variant titles: "A Gloss on 'Lycidas,'" "Lycidean Glosses"] (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - "No Continuing City" [variant title: "Summer Country"] (Box 16, Folder 28)
      - "Odyssey" (Box 16, Folder 29)
      - "Ornithological Section" (Box 16, Folder 30)
      - "The Osprey" (Box 16, Folder 31)
      - "Persephone" (Box 16, Folder 32)
      - "A Personal Statement" (Box 16, Folder 33)
      - "A Questionnaire for Walter Mitty" (Box 16, Folder 34)
      - "Remembrance Day" [variant titles: "Aftermath," "The Puppet Master," "No Requiems"] (Box 16, Folder 35)
      - "Rip Van Winkle" (Box 16, Folder 36)
      - "To Derek Mahon" [variant titles: "Birthmarks," "For Derek Mahon"] (Box 16, Folder 37)
      - "Words for Jazz Perhaps" [includes "Elegy for Fats Waller," "Billie Holiday: Blues Singer," "Bud Freeman in Belfast," "To Bessie Smith," "To Bix Beiderbeck"] [See also Uncollected poems, "Lady Day"] (Box 16, Folder 38)
      - "A Working Holiday" (Box 16, Folder 39)
      - No Continuing City, notes and tables of contents (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - No Continuing City, typescript [incomplete] (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - No Continuing City, typescript [setting copy] (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - No Continuing City [Macmillan edition], page proofs (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Lares (1972)
      - "Beds" (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - "Buster Keaton" [variant title: "Homage to Buster Keaton"] [See also Uncollected poems, "Explosion"] (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - "Celeste" [See also Uncollected poems, "Two Poems (2)"] (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - "Chaffinch" [variant title: "Bullfinch"] (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - "Eskimos" [variant title: "The North"] (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - "Ex-Champ" [See also Uncollected poems, "Two Poems (1)"] (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - "Farls" (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - "Furrows" (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - "Neighbors" (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - "Out of the Sea" [includes "Piranha," "Seahorses," "Bikini Atoll"] (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Lares, illustrations [by Brian Ferran] (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - An Exploded View (1973)
      - "For Derek, Seamus and Jimmy" [epigraph] (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - "The Adulterer" (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - "Alibis" [variant titles: "Apologia," "To Whom it May Concern," "Curriculum Vitae"] (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - "Altera Cithera: For Derek and Seamus" (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - "Badger" [variant titles: "The Badger Hunt," "The Hunt"] (Box 17, Folder 20)
      - "Caravan" (Box 17, Folder 21)
      - "Carrigskeewaun" [variant titles: "Behind the Cottage," "The Dry-Stone Wall," "The Strand"] (Box 17, Folder 22)
      - "Casualty" (Box 17, Folder 23)
      - "Confessions of an Irish Ether Drinker" (Box 17, Folder 24)
      - "The Corner of the Eye" [variant title: "Quatrains"] [includes "Kingfisher," "Wren," "Dipper," "Robin"] (Box 17, Folder 25)
      - "Doctor Jazz" [variant title: "Hello Central!"] [includes "Billie Holliday," "King Oliver," "Django Reinhardt," "Formby," "Keaton"] [See also Uncollected poems, "Masters"] (Box 17, Folder 26)
      - "The Fairground" (Box 17, Folder 27)
      - "Galapagos" (Box 17, Folder 28)
      - "Ghost Town" (Box 17, Folder 29)
      - "Images from Propertius" [variant titles: "An Image from Propertius," "Propertian Images"] [See also Uncollected poems, "Irish"] (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - "In Memory of Gerard Dillon" (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - "Irish Poetry" (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - "The Island"[variant title: "From the Island"] (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - "Kindertotenlieder" (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - "Lares [variant titles: "Turf," "Turf Fire"] (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - "Letters: To Three Irish Poets" (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - "Letters: To James Simmons" (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - "Letters: To Derek Mahon" (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - "Letters: To Seamus Heaney" [See also Uncollected poems, "The Residents"] (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - "Love Poem" (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - "A Nativity" (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - "Nightmare" (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - "Options" (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - "Poteen" [variant title: "Distillation"] (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - "Readings" [variant title: "Bandages"] (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - "The Rope Makers" (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - "Skara Brae" (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - "Swans Mating" (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - "Three Posthumous Pieces" (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - "To the Poets" (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - "Tutankhamen" (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - "The West" (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - "Wounds" [See also Uncollected poems, "For a Self-Portrait"] (Box 18, Folder 24)
      - An Exploded View, notes and tables of contents (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - An Exploded View [Gollancz edition], page proofs [photocopy] (Box 18, Folder 26)
      - An Exploded View, Longley's guide to arrangement of pages (Box 18, Folder 27)
      - Fishing in the Sky (1975)
      - "Cross Country" [variant titles: "The Harriers," "The Runners"] (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - "Mother Yoghurt" [variant titles: "Ritual," "Bowls," "Preparing the Milk"] (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - "The Owl" (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - "Stormy Petrel" (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Fishing in the Sky, notes and table of contents (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Man Lying on a Wall (1976)
      - "For Rebecca and Daniel" [epigraph] (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - "Ars Poetica" [variant title: "Eclogue Inside the Head"] [includes "Kathmandu," "Fancy Dress," "Arc de Triomphe," "General Release" [Now 18], "The Open Door"] (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - "The Bat" (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - "Belladonna" [includes "Genie," "Pelican"] (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - "Check-Up" (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - "Company" [variant titles: "The Cottage," "Holiday Home," "Watermarks"] (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - "Desert War" (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - "Dreams" [includes "Dream," "Sleepwalking"] (Box 19, Folder 13)